AdamH.Sparks

Plant Disease Management Specialist@IRRI

International Rice Research Institute (IRRI)

skills

GIS

modelling agricultural statistics

contact

IRRI

Los Baños, Laguna Philippines

Mail:
DAPO Box 7777
Metro Manila
1301 Philippines

a.sparks@irri.org

+63 (2) 580 5600 ****+63 908 182 8012 □
adam.h.sparks **⑤**

web

+AdamHSparksPhD **

@adamhsparks >*

adamhsparks (?)

personal summary

I am a plant pathology epidemiologist and ecologist who can effectively communicate and collaborate with diverse partners and stakeholders in an international setting. My work encompases traditional field-based research, epidemiological modeling, climate change, GIS and statistical methods. In turn, I use this work to understand what drives crop disease epidemics and derive disease control recomendations farmers and make recomendations for policy makers and other decision makers.

Scientist I

experience

since 2012

| | Develop tools and strategies for farmers to use in addressing rice diseases | |
|-----------|--|--|
| 2011-2012 | International Rice Research Institute (IRRI) Linked plant disease models with GIS tools | Post-Doctoral Fellow |
| 2009-2010 | Kansas State University Developed and refined predictive Fusarium head to | Post-Doctoral Research Associate blight models for wheat |
| 2002-2004 | University of Nebraska-Lincoln Managed maize and soybean plant pathology ext | Research Technologist ension field research |
| 2000-2003 | University of Nebraska-Lincoln <i>Managed maize and sorghum plant pathology ext</i> | Research Technician tension field research |
| 1999-2000 | Purdue University Coordinated training events for Purdue Diagnostic | Assistant Director Training and Research Center |
| 1997-1999 | Purdue University Managed soybean and canola production research | Research Technician ch studies |

education

| 2009 | Ph.D. Plant Pathology | Kansas State University | |
|------|--|-------------------------|--|
| | Plant Disease Epidemiology and Ecology | | |
| | Dissertation: Disease risk mapping with metamodels for coarse resolution predictors: global potato late blight risk now and under future climate conditions | | |
| 2007 | Graduate Certificate Geography Geographic Information Science | Kansas State University | |
| 2000 | B.Sc. Agronomy Soil and Crop Management | Purdue University | |

selected publications

Previous Five Years

Climate change may have little effect on global risk of potato late blight A H Sparks, G A Forbes, R J Hijmans, K A Garrett Global Change Biology (2014). DOI: 10.1111/gcb.12587

A review on crop losses, epidemiology and disease management of rice brown spot to identify research priorities and knowledge gaps

M K Barnwal, A Kotasthane, N Magculia, P K Mukherjee, S Savary, A K Sharma, H B Singh, U S Singh, A H Sparks, M Variar, N Zaidi

European Journal of Plant Pathology 136.3 (2013) pp. 443-457. DOI: 10.1007/s10658-013-0195-6

Taking transgenic rice drought screening to the field.

A C M Gaudin, A Henry, A H Sparks, I H Slamet-Loedin

Journal of Experimental Botany 63.2 (2012) pp. 695-709. DOI: 10.1093/jxb/ers313

An Economic Assessment of the Impact of Mango Pulp Weevil on the Agricultural Sector of Palawan, Philippines

J D Mckinley, A H Sparks, V O Pede, B Duff

The Philippine Agricultural Scientist 95.3 (2012) pp. 286-292

Complexity in climate-change impacts: an analytical framework for effects mediated by plant disease

K A Garrett, G A Forbes, S Savary, P Skelsey, A H Sparks, C Valdivia, A H C van Bruggen, L Willocquet, A Djurle, E Duveiller, H Eckersten, S Pande, C Vera Cruz, J Yuen

Plant Pathology 60.1 (2011) pp. 15-30. DOI: 10.1111/j.1365-3059.2010.02409.x

International agricultural research tackling the effects of global and climate changes on plant diseases in the developing world

S Savary, A Nelson, A H Sparks, L Willocquet, E Duveiller, G Mahuku, G Forbes, K A Garrett, J Padgham, S Pande, M Sharma, J Yuen, A Djurle

Plant Disease 48 (2011) pp. 1-40

A metamodeling framework for extending the application domain of process-based ecological models

A H Sparks, G A Forbes, R J Hijmans, K A Garrett

Ecosphere 2.8 (2011) art90. DOI: 10.1890/ES11-00128.1

Beyond yield: plant disease in the context of ecosystem services.

M R Cheatham, M N Rouse, P D Esker, S Ignacio, W Pradel, R Raymundo, A H Sparks, G A Forbes, T R Gordon, K A Garrett

Phytopathology 99.11 (2009) pp. 1228–36. DOI: 10.1094/PHYT0-99-11-1228

professional certifications

PRINCE2 Foundation (2014) candidate number: P2R/009385 - HiLogic Pty Ltd.

professional affiliations

American Phytopathological Society (APS)

Australasian Plant Pathology Society (APPS)

International Society of Plant Pathology (ISPP)

International Association for the Plant Protection Sciences (IAPPS)